<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A thanksgiving sermon preach'd upon the fifth of November, 1689 by Ben. Jenks.</title>
            <author>Jenks, Benjamin, 1646-1724.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46792</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J623</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28742</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10750147</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10750147</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45651</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46792)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45651)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1405:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A thanksgiving sermon preach'd upon the fifth of November, 1689 by Ben. Jenks.</title>
                  <author>Jenks, Benjamin, 1646-1724.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Benj. Tooke and are to be sold by R. Taylor,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Glory of God --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:45651:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45651:1"/>
            <p>A THANKSGIVING SERMON, Preach'd upon the <hi>Fifth of November,</hi> 1689.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Ben. Jenks.</hi> Rector of HARLEY in <hi>Shropſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Licenſed, <hi>November</hi> the 15. 1689.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Benj. Tooke, and are to be Sold by</hi> R. Taylor <hi>near Stationers-Hall.</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:45651:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45651:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE Francis Lord Viſcount Newport Of BRADFORD, TREASURER OF Their Majeſties Houſhold, And one of the Lords of His Majeſties Moſt Honourable Privy Council.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Muſt confeſs the Preſumption of this Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs, to ſeek ſo great a Patronage for ſo ſmall a Performance: But when nothing would ſatisfie ſome, without my conſenting now to
<pb facs="tcp:45651:3"/>appear thus openly; never durſt I think of expoſing ſo invidious Reflections, a Name remarkable for nothing but your Honor's Favours, under any weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſhelter than that which I now make bold to beg. But if what is here ſubmitted to common Inſpection, may find no further Approbation, but the bare for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givneſs of ſo piercing a Judge of Style and Senſe; I may harden my ſelf againſt the Shock of all other Cenſures. And the ſame Charity which was the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation to this Impreſſion, will, I hope, anſwer for all Imputations on your Honor's Judgment, for par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning a Piece ſo Mean and Dilute: Which if it muſt carry the ſound of my deſpicable Name, any further than the little Circumference wherein it is already known; I ſhall think it to good purpoſe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo far, as it ſerves to exemplifie the thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs which I Preach; in Publiſhing the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued Munificence of ſuch a truly Noble Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron, as, for above Twenty Years, I have found. To tell of which, I am Conſcious, I do my ſelf too great an Honor: But I had rather be charg'd with Oſtentation of ſuch Favours, than really in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur the worſe Guilt of Ingratitude for them.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:45651:3"/>
            <p>My Lord, I have not recover'd the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſport, which the late ſurpriſing Redemption gave me; and while I am entertaining my ſelf with ſuch da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ling Splendors, (as kind Heaven darted in upon us at the Critical Juncture, when a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of ill Omens were preſaging the moſt Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Night ready to Involve us:) I humbly beg ſome Indulgence, if (like the reputed Head of Infallibility himſelf, in the Transfiguration,) I ſpeak ſome things more Warm and Affectionate, than Exact and Appoſite. But whatever Ecſtacy the Wonder and Joy of this Reviving Scene have occaſion'd, yet of this I cannot chuſe but be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely ſenſible, that (beſides my own biggeſt Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations,) there's a juſt Debt of the higheſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and Gratitude, for which the Publick is Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponſible to Your Lordſhip, for your Conduct, ſo Wiſe, and Worthy your Noble Self, in that Happy Settlement, whereof we are glad. And however my forwardneſs to expreſs the Pleaſure I have taken in it, may already have render'd me as cheap as I can be, in the Opinion of ſuch as look with an Evil Eye upon that very thing, which others
<pb facs="tcp:45651:4"/>moſt cheerfully embrace with all thankfulneſs; yet cannot I omit any fit Occaſions of Declaring, That with all my Soul, I do Bleſs the God of Heaven for it. And as your Honour has ſtill been moſt deſervedly great in my Thoughts, on many other Conſiderations; ſo in particular, for your Honor's Favour to that Revolution, which eaſes the Minds, and exhilarates the Spirits of all Well-Willers to the Reformed Religion, I am more than ever,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Honor's ever Obliged, Moſt Humble Servant, <hi>Ben. Jenks.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45651:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. XXXIV. 3.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>O Magnifie the Lord with me, and let us exalt his Name together.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WHat was ſaid of that Concourſe, <hi>Act.</hi> 19.32. cannot ſurely be applied to any of our Congregations this memorable Day; That <hi>the Aſſembly was confuſed, and the bigger part knew not wherefore they were come together.</hi> The Fifth of <hi>November</hi> is a Day better known, as it is a Day ſtill to be much obſerved to the Lord of all our Iſrael in their Generations. And tho it were quite ſtruck out of our Kalendars, yet would it never be razed out of our Memories; eſpecially now that another wonderful Eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Eight has made it the <hi>Aera</hi> of our new Deliverance: And laſt year the happy Man of Gods right Hand, whom he made ſo ſtrong for himſelf, ſet foot on our Land the very ſame Day, as the Powder-Plotters were found dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging our Graves under it. This has not only afreſh ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veted the Memory of it in our Minds, but by reduplicat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the occaſion of our Thankſgiving, has made it to <hi>England</hi> now a high Day indeed, the day of the gladneſs of our Hearts, becauſe the day of our double eſcape; not only from the old Monk's Gunpowder, but from a new
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:45651:5"/>ſort of Jeſuits Powder, whereof they had laid large Trains, not only to blow up a ſingle Biſhop, and a College, but the very Foundations of all our Church.</p>
            <p>To themſelves indeed, (as the Event has made them ſenſible) a ſorry Blaſt it proved, to blow off even their Head; but to us a good Wind, that clear'd our Land of the Locuſts, which were got ſo buſily at their Work, to ſpoil all the envied Proſperity of this Flouriſhing Church.</p>
            <p>And as we cannot forget it to their Infamy, ſaying with the Prophet, <hi>Jer.</hi> 20.11. <hi>The Lord is with us as a mighty terrible One, therefore our Perſecutors ſhall ſtumble, and they ſhall not prevail nor proſper, but be greatly aſhamed, and their everlaſting Confuſion never be forgotten.</hi> As we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, I ſay, but remember both the later and former Plots, to the loſs of all their Credit in this Nation: (How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Woman in Scarlet may have a Face of the ſame die with her Garb, to leave no room for any modeſt bluſh;) So muſt we not forget to put an honorable note of diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction upon this Day, to the glory of God's ſingular Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; and to the exciting in our ſelves all the moſt thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Acknowledgments. Nor thinking it enough only to affect our ſelves, unleſs we endeavor to beget the like Reſentments in others: As thoſe, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 7.9. that ſaid one to another, <hi>We do not well, this day is a day of good tidings, and we hold our peace.</hi> ('Tis far from well to be liſtleſs and dumb to the Divine Praiſes, upon ſuch lowd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeaking Occaſions:) And like the devout <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> here, who calls upon all about him, to bear a part with him, <hi>O Magnifie,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:45651:5"/>
            <p>Of ſuch excellent Matter and Compoſition is this <hi>Pſalm,</hi> that <hi>Mollerus</hi> applies to it in particular, what St. <hi>Baſil</hi> ſays of the Holy Scripture in general: 'Tis like a Well which flows the purer, the more 'tis drawn, and the oftener attentively read, the ſweeter it will be found.</p>
            <p>It was compoſed upon a wonderful eſcape which <hi>David</hi> had, when flying, affrighted from one danger, he fell into another; and to avoid the Rage of King <hi>Saul,</hi> betook himſelf to the Court of King <hi>Achiſh:</hi> As more afraid of a ſtingy Father-in-Law, than of all thoſe very <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> whoſe great Champion he had lately ſlain, and with him all their hopes. 'Twas deep di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, (we may imagine,) that made him act as one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaved of his Senſes, to go caſt himſelf into ſuch Hands. But whatever was his deſign in coming there, ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing he had his Wits about him ſtill; yet as ſoon as he perceiv'd himſelf to be diſcovered, he thought it then time to renounce them: and by the Artifice of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonating one diſtracted before the King of <hi>Gath,</hi> he got himſelf a quick Diſcharge: For the King capitulat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with his Servants for bringing ſuch a Mad man to him, and ordering him to be turn'd out, ſo he was at his liberty again, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.10. to the end.</p>
            <p>It may be queſtioned, whether <hi>David</hi> did well ſo to act as a Cheat? But if the counterfeiting were his Frailty; yet that Deceit offers to our Obſervation this Truth, That God may deliver, even when men err in the means of Deliverance: And then his Glory is not the leſs, but greater ſtill, not to blaſt all the Succeſs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of ſome faulty Inſtruments. Tho it be the Lord's
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:45651:6"/>doing, yet if he pleaſe to make uſe of mens Concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to effect it, Men will be like themſelves; and no wonder then if there be ſomething in it that may lie open to Objection. He that can ſerve the ends of his Glory upon Sin it ſelf, and makes even the Wrath of Man to praiſe him; will not be ſo extreme to mark what his Servants do amiſs, as ſeverely to exact all their Failings; but mercifully allow for the Infirmity of our Frame, and the preſſure of our Temptations, and not preſently curſe every good Deſign, becauſe its Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moters may make ſome falſe ſteps in their Conduct.</p>
            <p>But no ſooner did <hi>David</hi> find himſelf got off the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipice, and begin to reflect on the mercy of ſo ſtrange a Preſervation, but he thought it was time to look up and bleſs the good Hand that had wrought his Deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. And ſo he breaks out in his Benediction, Ver. 1, 2. <hi>I will bleſs the Lord at all times, his praiſe ſhall ever be in my mouth. My ſoul ſhall make her boaſt in the Lord; the humble ſhall hear thereof and be glad.</hi> He knew that all the Servants of God who came to the notice of it, would be exceedingly affected with it; and therefore ſuch he invites to participate with him in the Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving: not thinking himſelf ſingle ſufficient for ſo great a Service, he ſummons in the whole Church to take a ſhare. <hi>O magnifie the Lord with me,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Where we have to conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Example and pious Practice of this Royal Prophet; it being implied, that he did <hi>magnifie the Lord,</hi> and <hi>exalt his Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:45651:6"/>
            <p>His Exhortation and earneſt Deſire expreſſed, that others would accord and ſtrike in with him; <hi>O magnifie the Lord with me, and let,</hi> &amp;c. I ſhall ſpeak of it, Firſt, as every one's Duty in particular; and then of its diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge in Conjunction with others. But to ſtate the thing in its proper Notion, before I urge our Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to it; let me ſhew what it is to <hi>magnifie the Lord, and exalt his Name,</hi> and how we are to perform it: And afterward what reaſon we have all to apply our ſelves to it.</p>
            <p>To <hi>magnifie the Lord,</hi> (in the letter) is to make him great; and to <hi>exalt his Name,</hi> is to raiſe the honor of his Works and Attributes, and all the Revelation of God, whereby he has made himſelf known to the World; his <hi>Name</hi> being himſelf as ſo diſcovered. Now here we are at a loſs in the very entrance of our Work, for that this thing does not look feaſible at all, nor likely for us ever to acquit our ſelves of it. To make the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme, the greateſt and beſt, higher, greater, or bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; alas, we are not able, 'tis utterly impoſſible. Let us not miſtake in arrogating to our ſelves that which is quite out of our reach, as if we, diminutive bits of God's Creation, could enrich the Exchequer of Heaven, or make him, to whom we owe our very ſelves, behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to us in the leaſt. Never muſt any man think ſo to be profitable unto God; for in this Conſideration, his Name is exalted far above all Bleſſing and Praiſe. And nothing of our aſcribing can make any manner of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to his Glory: No, 'tis not at all in himſelf, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in our own Minds, and others Eſteem, that we are
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:45651:7"/>capable of greatning and advancing the moſt Glorious and ever Bleſſed God, as the ſweet Singer of our <hi>Iſrael</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes it, <hi>In my heart, though not in Heaven, I can raiſe thee.</hi> We cannot make him, but his praiſe glorious, <hi>i. e.</hi> when we <hi>publiſh the Name of the Lord,</hi> and <hi>aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe greatneſs to our God, Deut.</hi> 32.3. When we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in our ſelves any worthy Sentiments, becoming the Divine Majeſty and Goodneſs; are fill'd with an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miring Senſe of his Tranſcendent Excellencies, and a grateful Senſe of his loving kindneſs: and endeavor, all we can, to propagate the ſame magnificent and fair Idea to others: This is the utmoſt whereof we are capable, to glorifie God in ſuch aggranding Repreſentations, as ſhew him ſomewhat like himſelf.</p>
            <p>Nor muſt we fondly imagine, that he who lacks nothing, affects to be honored, like ſinful Men, whoſe very defectiveneſs ſets them a gaſping after Vain-Glory: to be thought of higher and better than their Deſerts. The God of all Glory and infinite Perfections, as he cannot need the frail Breath and good Words of his poor Creatures; ſo 'tis infinitely below the moſt High, to intend what even a wiſe Man would ſcorn, only to fill others Minds with wonder, and be celebrated in the World.</p>
            <p>His Glory ſhining with a conſtantly equal Luſtre to his own Satisfaction, whether Men obſerve it or no: As long as he is infinitely pleaſed with the beauty of his own Actions, He concerns not himſelf whether perverſe incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent Judges approve or diſlike them; (any farther than they ſtand obliged by their own Duty and Felicity.) Nor
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45651:7"/>can we ſuppoſe him delighted in our Applauſes, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as our Well-doing is to him Well-pleaſing, and the Juſtice of the thing requires, that we ſhould render to him all Glory, from whom we receive all Good. For 'tis diſhoneſt indeed as well as unthankful, not to own whence we have every thing that is worth the having; 'tis ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiouſly to pilfer from him, what of all Reaſon and Right belongs to him. Tho it accrues nothing to his benefit, yet 'tis Robbery for us to embezzle it: And when his Name is polluted in the ſight of the Heathen, (which in it ſelf, its true, cannot ſuffer any Eclipſe,) tho no Affronts can hurt him, yet ought they to wound his Servants: Ill Reflections on their Lord muſt be as a Sword in their Bones, and the Reproaches of them that reproach Him fall upon them.</p>
            <p>According to the <hi>Greek</hi> Father's Paraphraſe,
<note n="*">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. S. Baſ. Hom. in Pſalm.</note> 
               <hi>He magnifies the Lord, who with a large Mind, and profound Contemplation ſurveys the great Works of the Creation, that through the Magnitude and Beauty of the things made, be may ſteal ſome glimpſes of the glorious Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of their being.</hi> And ſuitable hereto it is to form and preſerve in our Souls ſuch reverent Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of the Deity, as may humble us into the Duſt at the remembrance of his Glory, to whom all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are counted even leſs than Nothing and Vanity. Not to dreſs a God in our Fancy, ſuch a one as our poor ſelves, to worſhip our own miſconceits inſtead of the True God; who if we Adore not after the Canon of of his own Word, 'tis not ſo much honoring him, as
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:45651:8"/>humoring our ſelves, with the Will-worſhip not requir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at our hands.</p>
            <p>Tho here we need not ſeruple thoſe lowly Forms of Addreſs, which ſpeak us ſenſible of the vaſt diſproporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on between us, and our Glorious Maker; whoſe leaſt angry Finger on the Wall could ſo daſh a great King in the midſt of all his Jollity, <hi>Dan.</hi> 5. that the thouſand Lords his Gueſts, and all his Concubines, with the rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Fare, and Wine, and Muſick, could no more reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver him to his late cheerfulneſs, than they could ceaſe to admire his preſent Dejection.</p>
            <p>Nor is God leſs to be honored in his Merciful, than in his Majeſtick Relations; thoſe allaying the brightneſs of his Glory, and inviting us out of our Duſt, as with a Scepter extended, to warrant our Approaches. Indeed then is he moſt highly honored, when moſt dearly lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; for tho Fear may dwell with Hatred, Honor is ſtill the product of Love; which ſets upon its Object the greateſt value, and entertains it in the higheſt Room of the Soul.</p>
            <p>But we do rather Scandalize than <hi>Magnifie</hi> the God of Love: If we fanſie him in ſuch horrid Appearances as fill us more with dread than love; ſo that in our Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip we are only dragg'd to him, and never taken up delightfully with him; looking upon him, only as the Malefactor at the Bar eyes the Scarlet Robe, ready to appall the laſt reſidue of his Hope with a killing Sentence.</p>
            <p>We muſt not endure any ſuch Opinions of God, as reflect diſparagement on the Infinite Goodneſs, which ſo eminently declares his Greatneſs, in doing ſuch noble
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:45651:8"/>works of Mercy, as all the Power in the World could not, and all the Patience in the World beſides would not do.</p>
            <p>But when we behold him as the Father of Mercies, and Fountain of all Goodneſs, the moſt amiable Being, whoſe Love is as boundleſs as his Nature; from which Love the mighty Frame of Nature ſprang, and who ſo loved the World even when loſt, that he took the moſt amazing method for our recovery, to make us gainers even by the ſad loſſes of our Fall; putting our Salvation in much ſafer Hands, than when it hung only upon our own Free Will, and giving the ſureſt word of Promiſe, that he will put his Spirit in his People, which ſhall cauſe them to walk in his Statutes, and his Fear in their Hearts, that ſhall not ſuffer them to depart from Him: (ſo that we are kept now by the power of God himſelf through Faith to Salvation.) By this ſweet Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his firſt loving us, the Divine Love is apt to limn its own Effigies on our Souls, and powerfully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline us to him, as the bleſſed and only centre of their Reſt.</p>
            <p>And what greater thoughts of God can we conceive in our Minds, than to look upon him in Chriſt reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the World to himſelf, by that Redeeming Love, (which well may be ſtiled Ineſtimable,) whoſe preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſtrains chang'd our Judge into our Advocate, and made him purſue his Enemies with nothing but Bounty, and compaſs them about only with Songs of Deliverance? Here the heavenly Criticks themſelves can, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, lift up the Curtain to pry into this Myſtery of Divine Love; but even the Tongues of Angels are at a loſs, when they would turn the Admiration into Expreſſion.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:45651:9"/>
            <p>Never can we more highly <hi>exalt the Name of God,</hi> than to ſhew him to the World in ſuch lovely Repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, not only as the greateſt, but the beſt, that has done ſuch unſpeakable things, to approve his love, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage ours; and ſtill ſupplies a world of Creatures, that all depend on him for their Being, and every Comfort. There are ſuch Pleonaſms and Redundancies of his kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that a great deal ſtill falls even to their ſhare, who will never ſo much as thank him for it.</p>
            <p>And thus we do <hi>Magnifie</hi> the God infinitely Good, when we ſtand in admiration of ſuch Benignity, that we ſhould have any comfort with our lives, when we have done ſo much to ſpoil all with our ſins! Yea, that not a minute ſhould paſs but brings us a new fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor from above; and gives us more aſſurance ſtill that he deſires our felicity, and cannot deſign our ruin: who is love it ſelf, and hates nothing that he has made: delights not even in the death of ſinners, nor is willing that any ſhould periſh; indeed ſuffering none to periſh for the want, but only for the contempt of mercy; who ſtands not watching for advantages againſt us, but in fatherly conſideration of our Frame, makes merciful allowance for our Infirmities: and all Diſpenſations ſtill carry ſo ſweet a ſavour of good Will to Men, that not only when he gives us the ſmiles of the World, 'tis to draw us to himſelf with ſuch Cords of Love: but even when he threatens, it is to prevent the evils denounced: yea when he touches with the Rod, 'tis but to reduce us into the way of Bliſs, and ſuperſede our eternal ſmart. And thinking thus well of God, we do magnifie the Lord, and exalt his Name.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:45651:9"/>
            <p>To do all to the Glory of God, (an Expreſſion oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner us'd than underſtood) is ſtill to propoſe this End to our ſelves, that the great and good God may be more known and admir'd, rever'd and loved, believed and obeyed by us and all Men: aiming and endeavouring with whatever we are Maſters of, and all the intereſt we have in the World, to do ſervice to the Truth, and promote the credit of God's holy Religion, that it may look like it ſelf in us, and the way of Truth may not through our means be evil ſpoken of.</p>
            <p>And when by due Methods we earneſtly purſue our own felicity, ſo we bring God the greateſt Glory; But that we ſhould be willing to periſh our ſelves for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of his Glory, (as ſome have ſcrewd it up;) is a thing ſo harſh and extravagant, that the very naming it is enough to diſprove it, ſeeing God has wrought our Salvation in the frame of his own Glory, and he can have no ends in our ſerving him, but that we may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſerve our own beſt advantage. And this is the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt honor he expects from us, that we ſhould do all we are able to promote our own and others happieſt Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, in believing the infallible Truth of his holy Word, and making the greateſt Conſcience in all things to be determined by it. Nor only giving a total deference to his Will, but repoſing all our bliſs in his Hands. For we cannot honor one more than to reckon him worthy in all things to be hearkened to, and ſole-ſufficient to be relied upon, as the wiſeſt and ableſt, beſt and willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, to do us good.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:45651:10"/>
            <p>But the Properties of this Euchariſtical Sacrifice, and after what manner we are to offer it, (that it may be ſuch wherein God is well pleaſed,) we may gather from the Practice of the Man after his own Heart, here in the Context.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It muſt be with the Soul, from the Altar of a Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Heart. <hi>My Soul ſhall make her boaſt of God, Ver.</hi> 2. To glory in him, is one way of giving glory to him: (And well may we value our ſelves upon the honor to be obliged by ſuch a One.) And that this glorying may Imitate the Bleſſed Virgin's, whoſe <hi>Soul magnified the Lord:</hi> It muſt not be a verbal flaſh, like the crackling of Thorns on fire, but making melody in our Hearts to the Lord. Indeed if the Heart is not thankful, we are not at all thankful. The moſt pompous Halelujahs and Magnificats are no more than ſounding Braſs, and the tinkling Cymbal, if not the over-flowings of enlarged Hearts. <hi>The dead praiſe not the Lord:</hi> Hearts dead in ſin muſt needs be dead to the Divine Praiſes. And when matters ſo ſtand within, none of the Rhetorick of our complemental Harangues (ſpeak we never ſo good of his Name,) makes any Muſick at all in his Ears, who ſearches the Hearts, and requires Truth in the inward parts. Tho cavity of Inſtruments is requiſite in common Service, yet here hollow Inſtruments ſound harſh and hideous; and while they offer to praiſe God, only divulge their own ſhame. Yet, 2. Tho it muſt not be only a Lip-Service, we muſt not refrain our Lips neither, but let <hi>our mouths ſhew forth his praiſe. It ſhall ever be in my mouth, V.</hi> 1. 'Tis not to impriſon up our Thanks, ſo as to ſtifle the ſenſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:45651:10"/>we have of his Favors, nor hide his loving kindneſs in our Hearts, making them as the ſilent Grave to ſwallow up all: But out of their Abundance we muſt be ſpeaking to his honor, and not think it will ſully our Speech to mention the loving kindneſs of the Lord. When our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies are his Temple, and our Tongues the living Bells articulately to ſound his Praiſe; how can we better im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy the ſpeaking Faculty, than in celebrating his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that gave it? What we are tranſported with, we can hardly forbear to ſpeak of, if we are full of it, 'tis apt to float on our Tongues: And if the Mercies of God affect our Hearts, 'tis fit we ſhould expreſs the ſame, both to diſcharge a due Debt our ſelves, and alſo to kindle the like Flame in others.</p>
            <p>Indeed no Expreſſion here can be too much, that's without Affectation and Hypocriſie: Tho we not only extol him with our Tongues, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.17. <hi>But our Tongues ſpeak of his praiſe even all the day long,</hi> Pſal. 35. laſt. And we abundantly utter the memory of his great Goodneſs, (in a pious Vein flowing from the good Treaſure of the Heart,) accuſtoming our ſelves to ſpeak of the glorious Honor of his Majeſty, and of his wondrous Works; to ſpeak of the glory of his Kingdom, and talk of his Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; to make known the Fame thereof to the Sons of Men. As with Panegyrick pomp of Words, this Sacred Orator ſets it forth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145. And even this cheap Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation (for which we go not to the Flock or the Field,) ſhall not fail of a good acceptance above, when accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Exhortation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.15. We offer to God <hi>the fruit of our Lips, giving thanks to his Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:45651:11"/>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>To bleſs the Lord at all times,</hi> as Ver. 1. not only by fits, as it pleaſes us, or when extorted from us upon ſome occaſions extraordinary, but with ſuch a Heart,
<note n="*">Herbert.</note> 
               <hi>whoſe Pulſe may be his Praiſe.</hi> Our holy Living is the moſt effectual Thankſgiving. For ſo, <hi>while we live we ſhall praiſe the Lord, and ſing praiſes to our God whilſt we have our Being,</hi> Pſal. 146.2. To the offering of Praiſe therefore is preſently ſubjoined, <hi>ordering the Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation aright,</hi> Pſal. 50.23. And after he had ask'd, <hi>Who can ſhew forth all his praiſe?</hi> immediately he adds, <hi>Bleſſed are they that keep Judgment, and do Righteouſneſs at all times,</hi> Pſal. 106.2, 3. <hi>For as the Heavens</hi> (tho ſilent) <hi>are ſaid to declare the glory of God:</hi> (they are Preachers of his Praiſe,) becauſe their vaſt and beautiful Fabrick, their conſtant and regular Motions, their ſweet and powerful Influences, tell the Supreme Majeſty, the excellent Attributes, and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Perfections of him that there inhabits: So when we juſtifie the Divine Laws by our Obedience, and thus ſtand up to atteſt their high Reaſonableneſs and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, inſtead of repining at them as hard Sayings and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Burdens; ſhewing that really we do admire and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaud them for the bleſſed Products of an infinite Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Love, to contrive and effect our everlaſting Happineſs: Then do we give them the beſt Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, to make all enamour'd with thoſe Sacred Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which they not only hear ſet off in hollow Enco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miums, but ſee produce ſuch happy Effects. <hi>Herein is my Father glorified, that ye bear much Fruit,</hi> Jo. 15.8. <hi>The Fruits of Righteouſneſs are by Jeſus Chriſt, to the glory and praiſe of God,</hi> Phil. 1.11. That Men may ſo taſte and ſee, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:45651:11"/>bleſs the Giver of ſuch increaſe. <hi>I have glorified thee on earth, I have finiſhed the Work which thou gaveſt me to do,</hi> ſaith our Bleſſed Saviour. Joh. 17.4. Where he intimates that the doing of God's Will, is the way to Hallow his Name: When like the Luminaries above, that warm and move too, we ſend out the heat of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Love, and regularly move in the ſphere of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; without which indeed Honour is but an idle Complement, unleſs we ſo delight to do his Will, that our deſires like the Cherubims Wings ſtand diſplayed, ready even to ſpell out his Pleaſure, and prevent his Commands.</p>
            <p>But a ſad reckoning it would prove to us, ſhould we count that we are delivered to commit abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and make the bolder with God's Precepts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we have taſted ſo deep of his Mercies; as if his Goodneſs were our Warrant to deſpiſe him. Thus li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centious Men uſe to be worſt when they fare beſt, and in times of Feſtivity are the greateſt Brutes; not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how to be thankful and glad, without being wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton and mad. <hi>But ſuch as fear the Lord are call'd upon to praiſe him.</hi> Pſal. 22.23. And then do we moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptably ſing to the Lord a new Song, when we apply our ſelves to lead a new Life; when we look on our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, not ſo much a reward for doing well, as an opportunity ſtill to do better; not an occaſion to the fleſh, but an obligation to abound in his Praiſe.</p>
            <p>The thanſgiving of ill Men, 'tis but a fulſom ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rangue and offenſive noiſe; and indeed only reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Name of God, to ſpeak good of it, and do no
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:45651:12"/>good as becomes thoſe that profeſs it. <hi>Praiſe is comely for the upright, but 'tis marr'd in the Mouths of the wicked.</hi> It is a Sacrifice, and none but holy Perſons are to offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciate about holy things. As long as we live ungodly, we are in no capacity to praiſe God ſincerely: We never do it with all our hearts, till we offer up our ſelves to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with our thanks, and count a whole life too little to be ſpent in his ſervice, who has for ever obliged us to himſelf.</p>
            <p>Now all the reaſon in the World have we thus to <hi>Magnifie the Lord and exalt his Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For 1. It is the very end of our Being. And what was ſaid of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Iſa. 43.21. may be applied to us all, <hi>This People have I formed for my ſelf, that they ſhould ſhew forth my Praiſe.</hi> Man, as the Prieſt of this Inferior Creation, is to offer up a general Sacrifice, in the name and behalf of all the reſt; who in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral ways give a tacit conſent, and (as it were) ſay Amen to the Oblation: And when dumb and negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent to praiſe the Lord, we not only wrong our ſelves, but rob multitudes that would do it, had they but our faculties and abilities to reaſon and expreſs it. This is our Province, which the very frame of our nature ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apts us for, and even the whole Creation efflagitates and expects it from us: And we not only ſtand for Cyphers, but carry as an exorbitant rout, breaking our Ranks and diſordering the World, if we celebrate not his Praiſe who has ſo ſet us up.</p>
            <p>When we make a Man as they call it, and he is lookt upon as our Creature, whom we have render'd
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:45651:12"/>conſiderable in the World; we are apt to think he can never enough honor and thank us for it: But how do we cry out of the offenſive humour, if he be aſham'd to own what we have done for him, and rather ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lign us, for ſtanding as an Eye-ſore, to upbraid him with the Memory of his former low circumſtances, and his preſent high obligations? And do not we lye under the ſame imputation or worſe, when we ſerve not the Ends and Intereſt of him that in the fulleſt ſenſe has made us? 'Tis utterly inexcuſable not to pay him the poor Tribute of our thankful acknowledgment, which is all we are capable of rendring to the Lord, but to give him the glory of his own Gifts: Though we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not praiſe him according to the riches of his Grace, and the multitude of his Mercies; yet 'tis fit we ſhould do it to the utmoſt of thoſe capacities and abilities where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he has bleſt us.</p>
            <p>And when he has erected the World, not only as a ſpacious Theatre to ſpread far and wide his Fame, and the mighty Organ to reſound his Glory; but chiefly for the rich furniſht Medium, through which to derive the overflowings of his immenſe goodneſs, which can no more be confined than his Being; when 'twas not to better himſelf or ſupply any need of his own, but all for our ſervice and benefit; with a wonderful re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dundancy of pleaſures as well as neceſſaries, not only to ſupply our want, but ſweetly to entertain our very curioſity and delight: Shall we make no grateful returns to him that gave us our Being and every good of it, when he owed us nothing? Or ſhould he make Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:45651:13"/>that ſhould forget themſelves to be his Creatures; as if they were wholly independent, to live at large, and regard no ones pleaſure but their own; ſo proſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuting all thoſe Noble Endowments, that accompliſh them for the happieſt enjoyment of God himſelf, to ſerve nothing but ſome baſe Luſt or ſilly Vanity?</p>
            <p n="2">2. We have not only capacity, <hi>to magnifie the Lord and exalt his Name:</hi> but all manner of obligations to it; even common juſtice binds us to render to all their dues: And when by the grace of God we are what we are, there's the higheſt equity, that to the glory of God we ſhould do all that we do, and live to him as we live by him; nor arrogate to our ſelves or aſcribe to others, that which is his peculiar Right. Well may we extol him, when he has done ſo for us; that was well conſidered, Pſal. 30.1. <hi>I will extol thee, O Lord, for thou haſt lifted me up.</hi> If it be rude not to honor ſuch as have been kind to us, 'tis no leſs than impious not to honor him that made them ſo: How many great Luminaries elſe ſoever there be, all diſappear at the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Sun; and all other Benefactors muſt be even nulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to omnifie the Supreme.</p>
            <p>Now in this gratitude there's the greateſt juſtice as well as ingenuity; for there ought to be a reciproca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Courteſies, a due circulation in Friendſhip, and we muſt take care it do not ſtagnate and ſtick at us. And where the kindneſs of Noble Friends renders it impoſſible to retaliate, and abſurd to think of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation, (which were but to affront the generous Spirits that oblige us;) yet he that is capable of no
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:45651:13"/>more, can be thankful, and eſpouſe his Benefactors Cauſe, Love and Honour their Perſons, ſtand up for their Credit, and be glad and forward to ſerve their Intereſts. And what indeed is our whole Religion, but ſuch Gratitude? Still ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging the Debt we are never able to pay? All the dear Pledges of Gods Love are ſo many Mouths crying aloud for ſuch returns; and thankſgiving is but the eccho of received Mercies: But how ſwiniſh is it to devour the Bleſſings, and never look up whence they come? When 'tis indeed no ſmall endearment of every Mercy, (if we conſider it) to receive the ſame from ſuch Hands: For if we prize a gift for the givers ſake, how does it add to the value of the Mercy, that the Moſt High ſo condeſcends to concern himſelf in the care of us, and takes pleaſure in our proſperity?</p>
            <p>May our acknowledgments then bear ſome proportion to our engagements: <hi>For great is the Lord, and greatly to be praiſed.</hi> Pſal. 48.1. 'Twere endleſs to enumerate particulars, when we are ſo daily loaded with his benefits, they op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs us with their multitude, tho the precious things give us no Burden at all but what we delight in, and ſhould count it heavieſt not to bear.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As we are obliged, ſo by the goodneſs of it encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rag'd to it? <hi>'Tis good to ſing Praiſes to our God.</hi> Pſal. 147.1. 'Tis ſo with all the names of Good; not only a vertuous Good, doing the thing meet and right to be done; but as the Pſalmiſt reaſons there, <hi>'Tis pleaſant and Praiſe is comely.</hi> It gives the pious Soul a ſweet ſatisfaction, like the pleaſure which an honeſt Man takes in paying his Debts. <hi>My Soul ſhall be ſatisfied as with Marrow and Fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and my Mouth ſhall praiſe thee with joyful Lips.</hi> Pſal.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:45651:14"/>63.5. The moſt delicious Viands are not more grateful to a Healthy Body, than the Praiſes of God are to a well affected Soul. This raiſes us even into Heaven aforehand, to anticipate the Anthems of the Celeſtial Quire; and this helps moſt effectually to caſheir all black prejudices againſt a ſerious practical Religion, (as a ſour and melancholy thing;) when ſweet experience tells devour Souls the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, <hi>what a joyful and pleaſant thing it is to be thankful.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And how great is that Honor, to be taken up in the work of Angels? How much for our own praiſe to praiſe him, that has given us both matter and hearts for it? 'Tis no diminution at all, but the preſervation of honor and addition to it, for the higheſt on Earth to ſtoop lowly to the Supreme Majeſty of the World, who has promiſed to honor them that honor him.</p>
            <p>And tho this Duty ſeems to have nothing of ſelf in it, (as giving all unto God;) yet is it indeed (as all the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Religion,) much for our profit every way; for that it not only ſecures the bleſſings of God to us, but increaſes them ſtill upon us; he thinking them well beſtowed where they are ſo well reſented: And Praiſe provoking us alſo to an imitation of him whom we extol, thus it has a tendency to aſſimilate us to the Divine Perfections, and conſequently to prepare us for the everlaſting Glory; to bear a part with all Angels and Saints, in the Admiration, Love, and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Praiſe and Fruition of God in his Heavenly Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Thus as we are capable of <hi>magnifying the Lord,</hi> and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to it; ſo even in point of our own beſt Intereſt, we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nnot but be ſenſible what reaſon we have for it.</p>
            <p>And now (ſuitable to the deſign of this day,) conſider we the publick expreſſion of it, and its diſcharge in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:45651:14"/>with others; according to the invitation here given, <hi>O magnifie the Lord with me, and let us exalt his Name together.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He that was taken up even wholly in the Praiſes of God, himſelf, could not be contented to enjoy ſo much ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs alone; but as true goodneſs is ever diffuſive of itſelf, (and indeed does but ſtill add to its own dimenſions by ſuch Communication:) So was he for calling in partners to ſhare with him in ſo ſweet an entertainment. After he had led the Chorus as Prefect of this Muſick, he declares for a Conſort in it, and gives not a cheap exhortation without his own example: Nor is he for going in ſo good a way with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out company, but (to make the Communion of Saints a point of practice, as well as an Article of Faith,) he was for joyning all the ſparks to blow them up into a mighty Flame. And his Apoſtrophe is not only to the Children of <hi>Sion,</hi> but 'tis <hi>All ye Lands</hi> make a joyful noiſe to the Lord. Pſal. 100.1. 117.1. <hi>Praiſe the Lord all ye Nations, Praiſe him all ye People:</hi> And that none might be ſlack and backward, he not only calls on them, but upon God himſelf to quicken them. Pſal. 77.3, 5. <hi>Let the People praiſe thee, O God: Yea, let all the People praiſe thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He was not only for giving thanks apart in private re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, but for going into the Houſe of God, where Praiſe waiteth for him in <hi>Sion.</hi> Pſal. 65.1. <hi>I will give thee thanks in the great Congregation, I will praiſe thee among much People.</hi> Pſal. 35.18. To whiſper thanks in corners is but a tacit kind of denying received Benefits. <hi>Sen. de Benef.</hi> He car'd not how many Witneſſes he had of his thankſgiving; not for oſtentation of himſelf, but to excite an Univerſal com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance of the Church. A good Man would loſe much
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:45651:15"/>of the pleaſure of Heaven's Way, to move ſolitary in it: But here he gives the moſt charitable inſtance of his ſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Nature, to draw all that ever he can along with him.</p>
            <p>Indeed this is a kind invitation to Feſtivity as well as Duty; and here to devout Souls a hint is enough, though to dull Brutes a ſpur is too little: But to none can we offer a greater courteſie, than to importune their Society, in ſo delightful a Path to their own Happineſs. And ſuch as ſtand off here, are the moſt abſurd of all Diſſenters; and nothing fit to taſte of that good, for which they are too ſtiff to give thanks.</p>
            <p>Nor did this eminent Servant of God think himſelf too high to aſſiſt with his Inferiors in the Divine Worſhip; (that Spiritual Ordinary which levels all before him, with whom is no reſpect of Perſons.) So great a Prince was not aſham'd to own whence he received all: yea among the reſt, he calls on the Mighty to give unto the Lord Glory. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 29.1. For Princes and Grandees of the World (that have moſt temptations to forget God and exalt themſelves,) muſt lay aſide the conſideration of their greatneſs, when they fall down and worſhip before the Lord their Maker. No height in the World but muſt humble itſelf to him, who is higher than the Higheſt; and compar'd with whoſe Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotence all greatneſs elſe dwindles even to nothing. The Nobleſt Worthies in Heaven themſelves, do caſt their Crowns down before the Throne of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.10. and that does but faſter ſecure them on their Heads.</p>
            <p>But Oh! how much are they out in their ſenſe of honor, as well as defective in their conſcience of this duty, who offer to ſet up their own credit on the ruins of God's Glory! Indulging to the Popiſh humour of aſſuming to ſelf, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:45651:15"/>Idolizing Creatures, in derogation from the God of our Lives, and of all our Mercies. Truly Atheiſtical is it, ſo to live without God in the World; afraid to own him, but aſcribing all to a lucky hit, (this or that did the Work;) and no mention of Him that worketh all in all.</p>
            <p>When Men would be reputed great for being Ungodly, and like wild Horſes, in the carreer of their Impiety, caſt dirt at their Owner, as if they were neither in debt to him, nor in danger of him: As if it were below them, to own ſubjection to him that made them, Servile not to be above Duty, and a Diminution of their own Excellency to Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie Him. And if Conſcience extorts from them any acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgments of God, they are in care that none but himſelf may obſerve it, (who ſees indeed that they are aſham'd of him before Men, and ſo he will be of them one day, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the World:) Thus ſuch as uſe to glory in their Shame, are aſham'd of their Glory too. And tho all a fire at any diſgraceful reflection on themſelves, counting every thing leſs than flattery an affront; yet this gives a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious inſtance of their Baſtardy (which is the fouleſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy) that they can ſo eaſie brook a contempt of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father; thinking it fine to hear his Name Blaſphem'd, and his Word Burleſqued, and never ſtirring to aſſert his Honour, as they would, to vindicate the good Name of a Friend.</p>
            <p>Well may they dread the Fate of <hi>Herod,</hi> to periſh wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly, for not giving God the Glory: Or to be ſent with <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> to School to the Brutes, to learn to know their Owner: When they can live all upon his good things, and yet ſcarce afford him a good Word. Right Brethren in Iniquity, to Cabal for Miſchief, and run eagerly to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:45651:16"/>of Riot; to eat and drink and enflame Luſt, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute every one to heighten the Debauch; but none can find a Heart or Tongue to recognize the bleſſed Founder of all their Comforts: Or no ſooner is any thing to his Praiſe ſet a foot amongſt them, but 'tis frown'd upon, droll'd away, and hiſt out. Not ſo much as his Name muſt be mentioned unleſs in Oaths, for fear of ſpoiling all good Company.</p>
            <p>But beſides this Profane Generation, (that inſtead of joining to <hi>Magnifie the Lord,</hi> do nothing but vilifie, and would, if they could, even nullifie God: Inſtead of <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alting his Name,</hi> acting as 'twere in perfect ſpight and defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of him, who has told us, he <hi>will not hold them guiltleſs that profane it:</hi> Toſſing that tremendous Name in their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hallowed Mouths, as a thing of nought, and their Bleſſing and Praiſing is even nothing but Curſing and Damning.)</p>
            <p>There are others, (a new ſort of Nonconformiſts,) who peradventure will find, that they have not done well to be ſo angry, to ſtand off from contributing to make up this Harmony, to <hi>Magnifie the Lord</hi> with the reſt, and <hi>exalt his Name together.</hi> When 'tis ſo good and pleaſant for Brethren to dwell together in Unity; and beſt and pleaſanteſt of all to unite in the Praiſes of him who obliges and bleſſes us all. No Good Fellowſhip in the World comparable to this, when we can as readily concur to celebrate, as to participate the Bleſſings; that the Church may go up with general Shouts and Acclamations, and the noiſe of Axes and Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers in the Temple may not drown the voice of Rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and Salvation. That what is as Life from the dead to ſome, may not be as the ſhadow of Death to others.</p>
            <p>And O that in this ſenſe the Church would once ceaſe to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:45651:16"/>be Militant, and learn at laſt to accord in beginning the Eternal Triumph, with one Mind and one Mouth, to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt! O that Hearts and Tongues, and Pens might all agree here: that ſome may not be ſnagling as Saws, when others are running as oiled Wheels with enlarged Hearts! That we would not poſtpone the Publick Good to private Piques, nor ſhew our ſelves ſo mighty ſollicitous for our own little concerns, as for the Glorification of the Power, Wiſdom, Mercy, and Faithfulneſs of God, in appearing, as he has done, for his Church.</p>
            <p>But O what a Soil is that, wherein the moſt auſpitious Influences of Heaven produce nothing but Briars and Thorns! How contrary is this to him that brings good out of evil, when we are only for fetching evil out of good, and ſo full of Diſcontent and Contradiction, that there's no room at all in us for the Praiſes of God?</p>
            <p>Some may think it a great matter to be quiet; that the Government is much beholden to them, as extremely oblig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, when they ſay nothing, but vouchſafe only to hold their Tongues, and not load every one with Complaints, when the truth is, they have all the reaſon in the World to give Thanks, inſtead of making a Hubbub, as if ſorely pinch'd and wrong'd.</p>
            <p>But when every Malecontent muſt ſet up for a Pope, to make a whole Kingdom anſwer it at their infallible Bar, and damn all the Country that are not for driving juſt the ſame way as themſelves: The ſame Pride that has miſlead ſome, will hardly ſuffer them to own that they have erred. And then in what diſpoſition are they to admire the Goodneſs, and gratefully commemorate the Bleſſings of God, when
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:45651:17"/>they are All-a-mort, and even continually cruciating them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the matters, to them, croſs and offenſive? Here they ſit down reſtive and averſe to all Thankfulneſs, poring and hatching on their Grievances, till they overlook all that the gracious Lord has done for them, and grow not only rude and ſurly with Men, but ſour and ſullen even to God himſelf. Inſtead of that cheerful Spirit of Thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which makes Society eaſie and delightful, and ſheds abroad the ſweet Satisfaction, which is like Oil and Wine, to facilitate and exhilarate our motions; they hang the head, and tragically exaggerate the matters they take to be ill, and dolefully forebode worſe, to caſt a damp on their own Spirits, and exaſperate or deject all whom they can influence.</p>
            <p>And here every little buſie-body fanſies himſelf no leſs than an Atlas, to bear up the Pillars of the Earth, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port a ſinking Kingdom; betraying nothing ſo much as Pride and Ill-humor, Envy and Vengeance, a canker'd Breaſt, and a raw ſore Mind, unacquainted with the way of Peace. To lie barking at the Sun and Moon, which God in our doleful diſtreſs, has raiſed up, to illuminate and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh our Land.</p>
            <p>Thus Uſurping Judges make bold to ſhoot their Bolts, and dogmatize after ſome of their own preconceiv'd Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures; not allowing a ſtep out of the common Road, to unravel what others had ſo wofully perplext. Like idle Spectators on the Shore, ſtand cenſuring Mariners toiling in a Storm, for not obſerving every Punctilio in Mood and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure. They think Phyſick may be adminiſtred to a wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly diſtemper'd Body, without any diſturbance. When indeed conſidering into what Exigencies a Jeſuitical Conduct
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:45651:17"/>had caſt us, well may we wonder and bleſs the God who watches for good over us, that we are ſo well as we are, that all is not deſperate, and that any hopes of a better Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation than thoſe of late, are yet before us.</p>
            <p>No marvel if Papiſts hold themſelves agrieved, but mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring Proteſtants look now ſomewhat monſtrous, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd of ſuch Contradictions, as need an <hi>Oedipus</hi> to unrid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle them: when they would have their Religion Regnant, and yet they keep a Coil at the Extirpation of that which ſtruggled ſo hard to ruin it.</p>
            <p>How long ſhall the Lord bear with ſuch as deſpiſe all the Riches of his Goodneſs, and huff and piſh at Mercies too good for their betters, (becauſe every thing is not exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taſteful to their particular Appetites,) and hardly forbear to ſnap at the Hand that brings them all the Tokens of his Love? May not he expoſtulate with them, as <hi>Num.</hi> 14.11. <hi>How long will this people provoke me? and how long will it be ere they will believe me for all the ſigns which I have ſhewed among them?</hi> When ſtill we are as Incredulous and Miſdeeming, as if nothing at all had been done for us, nothing conferr'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us? And may we not thus tempt God to bring us yet lower, when we are ſo out of ſorts, that we are got no higher? O when will Duſt and Aſhes know it ſelf, and leave off ſuch Arrogance, and daring the free diſpencer of every Mercy, to turn us out of all?</p>
            <p>To contribute ſomewhat, if it be poſſible, to help us out of this ill Humor; to get that foul Jaundice out of our Eyes, which diſcolors the faireſt Bleſſings, and makes them miſtaken for Grievances and Calamities: That the Tares of our Diviſions may not ſtill prevail to choak the ſweet Fruits of our Thanks and Praiſe; that the ſtrings out of Tune may
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:45651:18"/>at laſt ceaſe their jarring, and vain jangling, and be wound up into an harmonious Agreement with the reſt, and change the <hi>Cynick</hi> Tone into the more becoming Accents of Praiſe and Thankſgiving to God, rejoicing in the Gladneſs of his Nation, and glorying with his Inheritance; that none may be ſlack or hal'd, to <hi>Magnifie the Lord, and exalt his Name;</hi> But all having a joint Senſe of the ſingular kindneſs of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to us, may conſpire as one Man, to give him the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor due to his Name: I would offer to Conſideration but theſe two things for a Concluſion; Our own ill deſerts, and God's diſtinguiſhing Mercies of late to us.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Our own ill deſerts. That we may not look on our ſelves as extraordinary Perſons fit for the Lord to take eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial notice of; but wonder rather that he ſhould at all open his Eyes upon us, and do ſo for ſuch; wonder it is no worſe with us, inſtead of grumbling it is no better. Ah Lord, how can a People laden with ſo much evil expect to receive nothing at thy hands but good? How do we forget our ſelves, when we are ſo curious and hard to be pleaſed? Muſt we have every thing juſt our own way, or elſe we'll turn back the Mercies of God, and croſly refuſe all, if he will not do for us exactly as we would have him. Muſt Slaves newly redeem'd out of the Gallies, ruffle and ſwag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger if they have not all Liberties, Gayeties, and Delicacies? Muſt the Obnoxious who have forfeited all, grow Inſolent, if they enjoy not the higheſt Privileges? and when we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve not a Drop or Crumb; will nothing but Fulneſs and Variety ſerve our turn?</p>
            <p>If Taxes and Troubles were harder upon us, if Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties and Dangers were yet greater before us, alas, what's all this to the Puniſhments wherewith the Righteous Judge
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:45651:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>of all the Earth might juſtly plague us? When it is of his Mercy we are not conſumed, ſhall we be ſick with Vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that we have any thing at all to affright or afflict us, and are not ſtill careſſed in the Arms of a cheriſhing Providence? O may we not only reaſon our ſelves out of the Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, but ſhame our ſelves out of the ill Manners of the thing; to Aſſault the King of Heaven's Door, if we are not preſently pleaſur'd with all that we have a mind to: When 'tis Mercy, if he hear and ſpare us at all, would we enjoy the whole of our Wiſhes on the ſudden, or elſe muſt go fill all places with our impatient Out-cries? When no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Fear, and Sorrow, and Suffering, is our due Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſhall we mutiny, as if a great deal of wrong were done us, if all ſucceed not juſt to our wiſhes? And howl like Wolves, if we are but threatned, and cry like Swine if we are but touched, yea, before we are touched, leſt we ſhould be?</p>
            <p>O let us give Glory to God, in Confeſſing our Sins, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we ſhall illuſtrate the Praiſe of his Power, Patience and Mercy in pardoning the ſame. Great Sinners muſt lay their Hands on their Mouths, tho they ſhould be great Sufferers. But, ah, what do we talk of Sufferings, when, on every ſide, we are ſo ſurrounded with Heaven's Bleſſings? And that we may not open our Mouths, unleſs it be in celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Divine Praiſes;</p>
            <p>Conſider, 2. (When 'tis impoſſible to recount all,) but God's diſtinguiſhing Mercies of late to us. For as 'tis the high En<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ment of Mercy, when it is vouchſafed to the unworthy, how much higher when the greateſt mercies are not with-held from ſuch as cannot lay claim to the leaſt? Novv beſides the great Deliverance from that helliſh Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:45651:19"/>which if it had taken effect, we had not been here to praiſe God, as we do, this Day: That he has broke the Teeth of the ungodly, who would now make us believe they did not mean to bite, becauſe they miſſed their hold: yea by a new Reſurrection of our Affairs, ſeal'd in the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of our Deliverer on Engliſh Ground this ſame Day, when they that hated us, yet ruled over us; he has tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed a new Life into our Hopes, and come in with the moſt ſeaſonable Reſcue, when, (like <hi>Iſaac,</hi> bound on the Altar,) we lay tied up, a Victim to Popiſh Vengeance, with the Knife at our Throats. That Men are not riding over our Heads, and the Sword is not ſheath'd in our Bowels; but we have been preſerv'd as Sheep in the midſt of Wolves, who were held back (with his inviſible reſtraints, that has his Hook in the Noſe, and his Bridle in the Lips of <hi>Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherib,</hi>) when they were ſet upon't to make ſuch havock, that the name of Iſrael might be no more in Remembrance. That our Air is ſo happily clear'd of the noiſom Peſtilence, which we were dreading, as ready to ſpread it ſelf all over our Land: That we have eſcaped the Brunt which has fell upon many of our poor Neighbors, and are at reſt in our Houſes, and ſecure in our Poſſeſſions, and (which is more than all,) at liberty to Worſhip God in the Beauties of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs; to go into his Houſe and pay him the Vows, which our Lips have uttered, and our Mouths have ſpoken, when we were in Trouble: That the Care of the higher Powers is imployed, not to undermine, but better Eſtabliſh our happy Eſtabliſhment: That the Throne is fill'd with ſuch Defenders of the Faith, and Guardians of our Country, as bear not an empty Title to abuſe us, but ſettle the Minds, and glad the Souls of all True-hearted Proteſtants, to have
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:45651:19"/>them there, before our Hopes, tho later than our Wiſhes. And not wading through Blood, to take Poſſeſſion, but call'd by a wonderful Providence, making the way plain before them; and Invited and Welcomed thither, by as general a Conſent, and univerſal Acclamations, as ever any were there.</p>
            <p>May we not now gather together theſe Mercies, as ſo many Precious Stones, of which to rear up an Altar for the Sacrifice of our Thanks, and call it our <hi>Eben-ezer,</hi> hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to has the Lord helped us? And where now is the ground of our Diſcontent? At what are any ſo peeviſh and Phren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick? Is it that ſuch as were coming to eat up our Fleſh, are ſtumbled and fallen? Is it that they have loſt the Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, to be Papiſts or Slaves? Is it that excellent Laws, and not an Arbitrary Will ſhall Rule us? Is it that a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Religion, and not Fulſom Superſtition, is own'd and countenanc'd throughout the Nation? Is it that the <hi>Sauls</hi> in their Career are caſt to the ground, and none ſhall be ruin'd for a Ceremony? <hi>Many good Works have I ſhewed you, for which of thoſe do you ſtone me?</hi> pleads our Saviour, <hi>Jo.</hi> 10.23. So may we capitulate with the Unthankful; Very worthy Deeds are done for our Nation; happy things brought to paſs; variety of eſpecial Immunities above moſt in the World do we enjoy: At which are they ſo netled, that they will never forgive their Deliverers? The healing wrought is manifeſt, and cannot be denied; but like the Malevolent, <hi>Act.</hi> 4.17. They are for ſuppreſſing the Fame, that it <hi>ſpread not among the People.</hi> And if it cannot be ſo held in; then it muſt be blemiſht with ſome of our Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. But ſuch queſtioning the Legality of Proceedings, is ſtill as liable to be queſtioned. For all the ſour Intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:45651:20"/>given, and hard Words ſpoken, (of an indelible Blot caſt on our Profeſſion,) ſuch Reproach need not break our hearts. ('Tis eaſie to put an ill Name upon any thing, and than run away ſcar'd with the Mormo of our own Creating:) The proof is yet to come, that the things excepted againſt, are what ſome make bold to call them. 'Tis, at the worſt, but a moot Point: But that ſomewhat elſe was highly unlawful, is no controverted Caſe at all. And to be ſorry that we are diſcharged from that Yoke is a ſtrein above Primitive Chriſtianity it ſelf, which never reſtrain'd its Votaries, from being glad and thankful, ſo to be rid of their Perſecutors.</p>
            <p>In the day when the Lord delivered <hi>David</hi> from the hand of all his Enemies, and from the hand of <hi>Saul,</hi> he ſaid, <hi>I will love thee O Lord, my ſtrength.</hi> Pſal. 18.1. <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be my Rock, and let the God of my Salvation be exalted. ver.</hi> 46. And does not ſuch high thankfulneſs become us alike ſingularly obliged? Not only the living Monuments, but the Mighty Wonders of the moſt Signal Goodneſs? When got out of the gloomy Shades of <hi>Babylon,</hi> to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs the Land; which again we may call our own: We have the faireſt invitation to lift up our Voices with our Hearts, <hi>and ſing the Songs of</hi> Zion.</p>
            <p>And in our high Eſtate, may we not forget him who remembred us in our loweſt: May not our Hearts be ſhut to him, whoſe Hand has been ſo open to us. O what ſo Charming Rhetorick, as to beſeech by the Mercies of God? And being under a ſweet Conſtellation of ſuch Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, O that we may feel their benign influence to tranſport us all into a cheerful Celebration of his Praiſes! And not be worſe than the dull Earth itſelf, which reflects the Rays
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:45651:20"/>ſent down upon it, nor ſtifle the Memory of his Benefits, who has done the greateſt things for us.</p>
            <p>As to which now we may ſay with the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> here, ver. 2. <hi>The humble ſhall hear thereof, and be glad.</hi> Indeed we want only to be humble to make us thankful: No ſuch bar to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, as a ſupercilious pride. The proud thinking all due to their Merits or below them, they are aſham'd to give thanks; eſpecially for ſuch things as others have done to their hands, but not juſt to their minds. Only to the humble God gives more grace; and ſuch Souls will he ſtill fill with his good things: Let us then be humbly ſenſible of, that we may be cordially thankful for, his Mercy.</p>
            <p>And as nothing will ſo ſecure the Bleſſings of Heaven to us, ſo nothing will ſtrike ſuch confuſion and dread in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Enemies of our Peace: Like as when of old, they began to Sing and Praiſe the Lord, the Enemies of <hi>Judah</hi> were all Defeated before them, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.22. Such bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed effects might we ſee of our ſweet accord, and uniting all to <hi>Magnifie the Lord and Exalt his Name.</hi> They that have long hop'd to reap their Harveſt, out of the Seeds them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have ſown to breed our Diſſentions, would then Hear and Fear, and no longer live in expectation, to ſet up their Dagon again: But be ready to throw their help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Idols to the Moles and the Bats, and go hide in Holes for fear of the Lord, and for the Glory of his Majeſty, when he ariſes to ſhake terribly the Earth.</p>
            <p>And then may we Bleſs God, not only for the Deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance begun, but alſo for our hopes of the Perfecting all that concerns us: If we will not reluctate againſt the Hand that is ſaving us, but be only contented to be Happy, and willing to ſee Glory dwell in our Land: We may find the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:45651:21"/>God of all Grace delighting yet further, to oblige the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of his former Bounty, and doing ſtill more for us becauſe he has done much already: In the experience we have had of his Mercy, lying all the beſt confidence we have of our ſecurity; that he will go on to ſhew Mercy, even for his Mercy's ſake, (making it a Motive to itſelf, Circulating by its own Spring in a Perpetual Motion;) and to compleat the Hiſtory of his own kindneſs, becauſe ſo long he has been <hi>Favourable to our Land,</hi> watch over us ſtill to do us good. To him (as we are moſt bounden for the Mercy of this Day, and for thoſe innumerable Mercies ſhowr'd down upon us every day, to fill even our whole Lives:) let us with the greateſt Sincerity and Cheerfulneſs, concur to Aſcribe all Glory, Thanks, and Praiſe, now and for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:45651:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
